Guide to the Stewardesses for Women's Rights Collection WAG.061
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Stewardesses for Women's Rights Collection
1966-1987
1972-1976
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Stewardesses for Women's Rights
WAG.061
3 Linear Feet in two record cartons, one oversize flat box, and one folder.
Stewardesses for Women's Rights (SFWR) was founded in 1972 after two flight attendants, Sandra Jarrell and Jan Fulsom, took Eastern Airlines to court on discrimination charges. The organization grew nationwide and worked to inform the public and other flight attendants about airline companies' sexist advertisements, company discrimination, and airline health and safety hazards. This collection includes correspondence, the constitution and by-laws, membership lists, and agendas. Along with general records, there is extensive research material from each of the SFWR task forces, records from affiliated unions, updates from regional offices, photographs, and papers from SFWR national conferences.
Related Archival Materials
Stewardesses for Women's Rights Oral History Collection (OH 012)
Custodial History
The materials making up this collection were donated by various former members of Stewardesses for Women's Rights after an SFWR reunion was held at the Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, NYU, in the summer of 1987. The reunion was organized and the collection assembled by Wagner archivist Brenda Parnes. The majority of the records were donated by former SFWR National Coordinator, Nan Frost Weimers.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
In the winter of 1972 two Eastern Airlines flight attendants, Sandra Jarrell and Jan Fulsom, took Eastern Airlines to court on charges of discriminatory weight and grooming regulations. These regulations, enforced against female flight attendants but not against their male co-workers, led both women to leave their jobs, claiming their working conditions were unreasonably stressful. Consequently, the two women joined with other flight attendants to address working conditions and discrimination within the airline industry to form Stewardesses for Women's Rights (SFWR). The response from flight attendants was immediate and substantial. The SFWR national headquarters (opened in early 1974) was at Rockefeller Center in New York City, and there were regional offices throughout the United States. The first national conference of SFWR, held in March 1973, was addressed by Gloria Steinem, who had recently founded Ms. Magazine. Steinem continued to be a strong supporter of the organization throughout its brief existence.
As part of its services, the organization published a newsletter (Stewardesses for Women's Rights) ten times yearly. In it SFWR informed its members of sexist advertising, company discrimination, and health and safety hazards in the airline industry. SFWR also wrote and produced a counter-commercial that emphasized the flight attendant as a responsible professional within the airline industry rather than a glamour girl. Also, SFWR served as a legal liaison, linking stewardesses who had been discriminated against by airline companies to lawyers who could successfully defend them. Many stewardesses were restored to their jobs with full back pay and benefits as a result of asking SFWR for help. A number of individuals were reinstated in their jobs and won considerable back pay judgments after approaching SFWR for help. SFWR also helped change discriminatory policies of airline companies. In time tensions developed within the organization; some members saw their struggle primarily in feminist terms, and others were interested in traditional labor organizing. Some left to devote their time more exclusively to union activity. Due to declining membership and lack of funding, SFWR folded in the spring of 1976.
Scope and Content Note
This artificial collection is made up of materials on the Stewardesses for Women's Rights, donated by multiple former members of the group. This collection includes correspondence, the constitution and by-laws, membership lists, and agendas. Along with general records, there is extensive research material from each of the SFWR task forces, records from affiliated unions, updates from regional offices, photographs, exhibit materials, textiles, and papers from SFWR national conferences.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into four series:
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Subject Files
Series III: Task Forces
Series IV: Visual Materials and Artifacts
Files in each series are alphabetized.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by various former members of the Stewardesses for Women's Rights, 1987. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 1987.019, 1987.020, and 1987.021.
Reports.; Sex discrimination against women -- United States.; Correspondence.; Flight attendants |z United States.; Fliers (printed matter); Clippings (information artifacts); Eastern Air Lines; Transport Workers Union of America; Welmers, Nan Frost; Jarrell, Sandra; Stewardesses for Women's Rights
- Series I: Correspondence, 1973-1975
  Scope and Content Note
  This series includes general correspondence between the Stewardesses for Women's Rights (SFWR) main office and other labor and feminist organizations. There are letters to and from Sandra Jarrell, co-founder and former national coordinator of SFWR, including letters from other SFWR members and organizers. These letters detail organizing tactics as well as the SFWR leadership's responsibilities. Also contained are letters to former SFWR national coordinator Nan Frost Welmers from members and other organization leaders. The Legal Task Force correspondence includes letters from flight attendants seeking legal assistance as well as responses and advice from the task force. Membership correspondence consists of letters from flight attendants to SFWR.
  - Correspondence: General, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Jarrell, Sandra: Correspondence, circa 1973-1967, 1980-1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Legal Task Force: Correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Membership: Correspondence, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Welmers, Nan Frost: Correspondence, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1966-1987
  This series contains organizational documents including the constitution, by-laws, membership lists, minutes, agendas, and update reports. Also included are research materials that SFWR staff collected, such as articles, essays, clippings, and handbooks. The series contains documents from flight attendant unions, the Transport Workers Union of America (TWU), and various women's organizations.
  - Applications for Flight Attendants, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Articles and Essays, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Board Members: List, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Booklets and Flyers, undated, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Brochures: Flight Attendant School, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, 1974-1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Constitution and By-Laws, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Financial: Tax Status, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Fundraising, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Handbook: Organizing, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Kane, Paula and Chandler, Christopher: Sex Objects in the Sky (advance copy), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Magazines: Trade and Professional, 1974-1986 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Manual: Pan American Flight Service, 1966-1968, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Membership Lists, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Minutes and Agendas, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous Publications, 1975-1987 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - National Conference, Spring 1973 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - National Conference, Fall 1973 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - National Conference, Spring 1974 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - National Conference, Fall 1974 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - National Conference, Fall 1975 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Newsletter Updates, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Operations: New York Office, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Planning and Organizing, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Reunion, Apr 22, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Transport Workers Union: Air Transport Division Local 551, 1973-1977 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Transport Workers Union of America (TWU): Labor Protective Provisions, Apr 3, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Unions: Flight Attendant, 1967-1978 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Update Reports: New York Office, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Update Reports: Northeastern Region, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Update Reports: Southern Region, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Update Reports: Western Region, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Wages and Benefits, undated, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Women's Organizations, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Women's Rights Day, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Series III: Task Forces, 1972-1978
  This series contains materials collected by SFWR task forces: the health and safety task force, the legal task force, the public relations task force, and the educational program, Safe Transportation of People (STOP). Each task force obtained articles, essays, notes, and legal case files that could aid the specific task force. All the task force files consist of articles, clippings, and reports on their respective issues. The legal task force files include extensive documents on jurisdiction and complaints filed by flight attendants for sexual harassment, sexual discrimination, and weight requirements.
  - Health and Safety Task Force: Crashes, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Health and Safety Task Force: Dysrhythmia, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Health and Safety Task Force: General, 1972-1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Health and Safety Task Force: Hazardous Cargoes, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Health and Safety Task Force: Hypoglycemia, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Health and Safety Task Force: Menstrual Cycle, Pregnancy, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Health and Safety Task Force: Ozone, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Health and Safety Task Force: Radiation, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Health and Safety Task Force: Smoking/Cabin Ventilation, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Legal Task Force: Cases (1), 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Legal Task Force: Cases (2), 1973-1976 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Legal Task Force: F/A Weight Requirements, 1973-1976 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Legal Task Force: Non-Airline Cases, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Legal Task Force: Sex Discrimination/Sexual Harassment, undated, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Public Relations Task Force: Media Image/Sexist Advertising, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Public Relations Task Force: Membership Recruitment, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Public Relations Task Force: Publicity, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Safe Transportation of People (STOP), 1975 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Task Forces: General, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Series IV: Visual Materials and Artifacts, 1970s-1987
  This series contains visual and ephemeral materials on Stewardesses for Women's Rights (SFWR). Approximately half of this series is made up of black-and-white and color photographs and slides, depicting SFWR meetings and demonstrations. A portion of the photographs comes from a disassembled scrapbook of members creating a quilt. Some notable individuals in the photos include Betty Friedan and Gloria Steinem. The other half of the materials is likely from an 1987 exhibit and reunion of members at Tamiment for the opening of the collection. These materials are made up placards from the exhibit and other materials donated by the members of SFWR, including a t-shirt and other textiles, photographs, letterheads, stickers, buttons, advertisements, fliers, and other ephemera.
  - "Coffee, Tea, or Fly Me" Ad [Exhibit?], undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - [Color Snapshots from disassembled scrapbook], undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Demonstrations and Meetings Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Exhibit Materials, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Exhibit Materials, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Exhibit Materials and Photograph (Box Tamiment Shared OS005)
  - Stewardesses for Women's Rights Stickers and other Ephemera, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Stewardesses Group Slides, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Textiles, undated (Box 3)
  - SFWR Graphic, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 028, Folder 4)